<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Economics</title>
<link>https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.43</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 16:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>More Than a Weight Problem: How Obesity Is Affecting College Students Around the World</title>
  <dc:creator>Dr. Swadhin Mondal</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/posts/obesity/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="the-silent-epidemic-on-campus" class="level1">
<h1>The Silent Epidemic on Campus</h1>
<p>Step onto any college campus — whether in Muscat, Mumbai, London, or New York — and you’ll see a familiar pattern: students skipping breakfast, relying on fast food, spending long hours sitting in front of screens, and getting little physical activity. This lifestyle — marked by poor diet, sedentary habits, and high stress — is quietly fueling a growing concern that’s reshaping the landscape of higher education: obesity among young adults.</p>
<p>Obesity has traditionally been seen as a middle-aged problem. But research over the past decade shows a worrying rise in obesity rates among university students. These are individuals at a formative stage of life, where habits — good or bad — tend to last. And the consequences go far beyond health.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-healtheducation-connection" class="level1">
<h1>The Health–Education Connection</h1>
<p>Recent studies, including our research at the University of Nizwa, reveal that obesity doesn’t only affect physical wellbeing — it also influences academic performance, motivation, and mental health. College students with obesity are significantly more likely to experience:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lower academic performance, often linked to poor concentration, fatigue, and absenteeism.</li>
<li>Increased risk of anxiety and depression, partly due to stigma or body image issues.</li>
<li>Early onset of chronic conditions such as hypertension, type 2 diabetes, and sleep disorders.</li>
<li>Reduced participation in sports, social events, and group learning, leading to isolation.</li>
</ul>
<p>In our study, obese students scored 6–7% lower on average than their healthy-weight peers. This finding echoes global research from the U.S., U.K., and Asia showing that obesity correlates with lower GPA and poorer cognitive outcomes — even when adjusting for socioeconomic factors.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-college-students-are-vulnerable" class="level1">
<h1>Why College Students are Vulnerable</h1>
<p>College life is often the first time young people manage their own schedules, diets, and routines. For many, this independence brings unstructured eating, irregular sleep, and sedentary habits driven by academic pressure and digital lifestyles.</p>
<p>Some key risk factors include:</p>
<ul>
<li>High consumption of fast food and sugary drinks due to convenience and cost.</li>
<li>Stress-related overeating, especially during exams or social transitions.</li>
<li>Limited physical activity, as academic workloads and screen time replace movement.</li>
<li>Social factors, such as peer pressure, poor self-image, or cultural norms around body size.</li>
</ul>
<p>Socioeconomic background also matters — students from lower-income families often face barriers to accessing healthy food or fitness facilities, turning obesity into both a health and equity issue.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-ripple-effects-health-career-and-society" class="level1">
<h1>The Ripple Effects: Health, Career, and Society</h1>
<p>The effects of obesity during college years can extend far into adulthood. Physically, early obesity raises lifetime risk for cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and certain cancers. Mentally, it can erode confidence, affect employability, and influence career progression — particularly in fields where appearance or energy levels play a role.</p>
<p>At a societal level, the growing prevalence of obesity among educated youth is alarming. These students represent tomorrow’s workforce, leaders, and innovators. Their health trajectory directly affects national productivity and healthcare costs.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-this-matters-for-policy" class="level1">
<h1>Why This Matters for Policy</h1>
<p>This research underscores the importance of recognizing youth obesity as a policy priority. Its effects extend from health to education and employment — key pillars of national development. By impairing academic achievement and limiting career prospects, obesity reduces young people’s human capital and lifetime earnings potential. Yet, the evidence also offers hope: early interventions in nutrition, physical activity, and mental health can mitigate these effects, improving both educational outcomes and future socioeconomic mobility.</p>
</section>
<section id="building-healthier-campuses" class="level1">
<h1>Building Healthier Campuses</h1>
<p>Addressing obesity among college students requires more than individual willpower — it needs systemic change. Universities can play a transformative role by creating environments that promote physical and mental wellbeing.</p>
<p>Key actions include:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Healthy Campus Dining: Replace calorie-dense options with affordable, nutritious meals.</li>
<li>Active Campus Culture: Provide fitness facilities, walking tracks, and activity clubs.</li>
<li>Mental Health Support: Tackle stress and body image issues through counseling.</li>
<li>Health Literacy: Integrate nutrition and lifestyle education into orientation programs.</li>
<li>Peer Support Initiatives: Encourage group-based wellness activities and accountability.</li>
</ol>
<p>When health becomes part of campus culture, students not only learn better — they live better.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-call-for-action" class="level1">
<h1>A Call for Action</h1>
<p>The fight against obesity isn’t just about diet or exercise; it’s about redefining what it means to succeed in higher education. Academic excellence should include health literacy, self-care, and resilience.</p>
<p>Universities and policymakers have a shared responsibility to ensure that young people graduate not only with degrees — but also with the health and energy to use them well.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled" title="About the Author">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the Author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Swadhin Mondal is an economist and researcher specializing in public health, quantitative methods, and development policy. His recent study, “Obesity among college students in Oman: Implications for health and academic performance,” was published in BMC Public Health (2025) and examines the relationship between obesity, health, and educational outcomes among university students.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/posts/obesity/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/posts/obesity/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Research Publication in BMC Public Health</title>
  <dc:creator>Dr. Swadhin Mondal</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/posts/paper/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m happy to share that my article, titled “Obesity among college students in Oman: implications for health and academic performance”, has been published in BMC Public Health!</p>
<p><img src="https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/posts/paper/thumbnail.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled" title="Abstract">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Abstract
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This study examines the impact of obesity on the current health and academic performance of college students, with potential long-term implications for their overall well-being. Using survey data from 300 students at a university in the Arab Gulf of Oman, the study finds that over 27% of students are classified as overweight or obese. The analysis reveals a significant negative relationship between obesity and academic performance, with obese students showing a 6.6% decrease in academic grades compared to their peers of healthy weight. The findings suggest that the likelihood of earning lower academic grades is 2.54 times higher among obese students than those with normal weight. Additionally, the study indicates that obese students face an 8.5% higher burden of obesity-related health issues and are 5.77 times more likely to develop such conditions compared to normal-weight students. These results highlight that obesity affects both academic achievement and health, with potential long-term consequences for students’ well-being. To address these issues, educational institutions and communities should prioritize promoting healthy lifestyles, including proper nutrition and weight management support.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Please take a look at the full article <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12889-025-21946-7">here</a>!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <guid>https://rbiswasfc.github.io/sw-blog/posts/paper/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2025 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
